Dearborn Group Records 5569
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Dearborn Group Records
1951-1973
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Dearborn Group
5569
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Records (documents), correspondence.
Biannual meeting minutes, research files, and correspondence.
3336266
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 10, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 29, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Dearborn Conference Group is an organization of directors of Industrial Relations Research Departments in several large U.S. corporations.
The Dearborn Group includes representatives from major corporations in the automotive, chemical, food processing, paper manufacturing, petroleum, petrochemical, steel, telecommunications and textile industries as well as corporate officers with similar responsibilities representing major utilities, the retail trade and an insurance carrier. Their objectives in meeting as a group are the futherance of industrial relations research methodology, information exchange about industrial relations experiences, and the promotion of industrial relations research.
Scope and Contents
The Dearborn Conference Group's records consist of files relating to its biannual meetings, 1951-1971 (4 bound volumes), research files (6 bound volumes) arranged in alphabetical order by corporate name, and correspondence between Conference Group participants on the Group's activities (4 volumes).
The meeting files consist of agenda, minutes, reports, summaries of accomplishments, and supporting correspondence. Research activities regarding particular aspects of labor-management relations and personnel management, including methods of predicting and measuring leadership abilities, techniques for the management and development of employees, performance appraisal, and the evaluation of future trends in personnel management, especially union activities and trends in benefits, are discussed both at the meeting and in subsequent correspondence.
The corporate research project files contain outlines and reports of then current industrial relations projects with supporting documentation. Included are studies on compensation (wages and hours), benefit plans, internal management planning, employee selection, employee development, employee testing, safety education and programs, labor-management relations, and trends in collective bargaining, among other issues.
Compilation of materials regarding the biannual Dearborn Conference Meetings, including agenda, minutes, reports, correspondence, memoranda, notes and summaries.
The Dearborn Conference Group's records consist of files relating to its biannual meetings, 1951-1971 (4 bound volumes), research files (6 bound volumes) arranged in alphabetical order by corporate name, and correspondence between Conference Group participants on the Group's activities (4 volumes).
The meeting files consist of agenda, minutes, reports, summaries of accomplishments, and supporting correspondence. Research activities regarding particular aspects of labor-management relations and personnel management, including methods of predicting and measuring leadership abilities, techniques for the management and development of employees, performance appraisal, and the evaluation of future trends in personnel management, especially union activities and trends in benefits, are discussed both at the meeting and in subsequent correspondence.
The corporate research project files contain outlines and reports of then current industrial relations projects with supporting documentation. Included are studies on compensation (wages and hours), benefit plans, internal management planning, employee selection, employee development, employee testing, safety education and programs, labor-management relations, and trends in collective bargaining, among other issues.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5634: Dearborn Group Additional Records
Automobile industry workers -- United States; Chemical workers -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Automobile industry -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Chemical industry -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Paper industry -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Petroleum industry -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Steel industry -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Telecommunication -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Textile industry -- United States; Employee selection -- United States; Employee training directors -- United States; Executives -- Training of -- United States; Food industry -- Employees -- United States; Industrial relations -- Research -- United States; Job evaluation -- United States; Paper industry workers -- United States; Employees -- Rating of; Personnel directors; Personnel management -- United States; Personnel management -- Research; Petroleum chemicals industry -- Industrial relations -- United States; Petroleum industry -- Employees -- United States; Retail trade -- Employees -- United States; Safety education, Industrial; Steel industry and trade -- Employees -- United States; Telecommunication -- Employees -- United States; Textile industry -- Employees -- United States; Wages -- United States; Dearborn Conference Group
3336266
- "Selectied Highlights from Dearborn's First Decade, 1951-1959." by Robert Barmein; "Dearborn Conference File Summary of Contents." June, 1955; "Dearborn Conference." Reports, Statements, and Surveys. (Box 1)
  - Dearborn Conference File Summary, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Large booklet containing appendices
  - Selected Highlights from Dearborn Group's First Decade, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    "Confidential" summaries by date; 5/21/1951 - 10/22- 3/1959
  - Dearborn Conference Group, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Management Development Objectives" March 8 1955
  - "Dearborn Conference", 1951-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Research and Information
  - "Dearborn Conference", 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes biographies, etc.
  - "Dearborn Conference", 1952-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Dearborn Conference." Reports, Statements, and Surveys, AT&T- U.S. Rubber. (Box 2)
  - Dearborn Conference, 1951-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains highly detailed information on companies
  - Dearborn Group, 1951-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dearborn Group, 1952-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Dearborn Conference." Reports, Statements, and Surveys, AT&T- U.S. Rubber; "Dearborn Conference Meetings." 1951-1973. (Box 3)
  - Dearborn Conference Meetings, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dearborn Conference Meetings, 1955-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dearborn Conference Meetings, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dearborn Conference, 1951-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Some papers labeled "Confidential"
  - Dearborn Conference, 1952-1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dearborn Conference, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Contains a study on employees by race and ethnicity
- "Dearborn Conference Meetings." 1951-1973; "Dearborn Conference- General Correspondence and Exchange. American Cork- Socony Vacuum.". (Box 4)
  - Dearborn Conference Meetings, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Dearborn Conference Meetings, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Dearborn Conference Meetings, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    November 11-12, 1971
  - Dearborn Conference Meetings, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Industry and Employee Relations Research, 1951-1959 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    5/21/1951 - 10/22-23/1959; "Confidential"
  - Dearborn Conference, Correspondence and Exchange, 1951-1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and Exchange, General., 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Dearborn Conference, Correspondence and Exchange, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)